<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Amanda Cercas Curry - Amanda Cercas Curry</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/amanda-cercas-curry.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2023-12-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Impoverished Language Technology: Social Class in NLP</title><link href="/impoverished-language-technology-social-class-in-nlp.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-12-03T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-12-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Amanda Cercas Curry</name></author><id>tag:None,2023-12-03:/impoverished-language-technology-social-class-in-nlp.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Since the foundational work of William Labov on the social stratification of language, linguistics has made concentrated efforts to explore the links between socio-demographic characteristics and language production and perception.
But while there is strong evidence for socio-demographic characteristics in language, they are infrequently used in Natural Language Processing (NLP …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Since the foundational work of William Labov on the social stratification of language, linguistics has made concentrated efforts to explore the links between socio-demographic characteristics and language production and perception.
But while there is strong evidence for socio-demographic characteristics in language, they are infrequently used in Natural Language Processing (NLP). Age and gender are somewhat well represented, but Labov's original target, socioeconomic status, is noticeably absent. And yet it matters. We show empirically that NLP disadvantages less-privileged socioeconomic groups. 
We annotate a corpus of 95K utterances from movies with social class, ethnicity and geographical language variety and measure the performance of NLP systems on three tasks: language modelling, automatic speech recognition, and grammar error correction. 
We find significant performance disparities that can be attributed to socioeconomic status as well as ethnicity and geographical differences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With NLP technologies becoming ever more ubiquitous and quotidian, % present in our everyday lives, 
they must accommodate all language varieties to avoid disadvantaging already marginalised groups. 
We argue for the inclusion of socioeconomic class in future language technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collaborators:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Giuseppe Attanasio&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zeerak Talat&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dirk Hovy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Research"></category></entry><entry><title>Thinking About Harms, Offensiveness and Hate Speech</title><link href="/thinking-about-harms-offensiveness-and-hate-speech.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-12-03T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-12-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Amanda Cercas Curry</name></author><id>tag:None,2023-12-03:/thinking-about-harms-offensiveness-and-hate-speech.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Natural language processing research has begun to embrace the notion of annotator subjec-
tivity, motivated by variations in labelling. This approach understands each annotator’s view as valid, which can be highly suitable for tasks that embed subjectivity, e.g., sentiment analysis. However, this construction may be inappropriate for tasks …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Natural language processing research has begun to embrace the notion of annotator subjec-
tivity, motivated by variations in labelling. This approach understands each annotator’s view as valid, which can be highly suitable for tasks that embed subjectivity, e.g., sentiment analysis. However, this construction may be inappropriate for tasks such as hate speech detection, as it affords equal validity to all positions on e.g., sexism or racism. We argue that the conflation of hate and offence can invalidate findings on hate speech, and call for future work to be situated in theory, disentangling hate from its orthogonal concept, offence.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Research"></category></entry><entry><title>Penelope: Emotions in NLP</title><link href="/penelope-emotions-in-nlp.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-06-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-06-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Amanda Cercas Curry</name></author><id>tag:None,2023-06-01:/penelope-emotions-in-nlp.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In this multidisciplinary project we bring together philosophy, psychology and NLP to explore emotion analysis and related tasks in NLP. So far, we conducted a survey of the field in recent years, focusing in particular in the types of frameworks used in NLP research. 
We also showed that Large Language …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In this multidisciplinary project we bring together philosophy, psychology and NLP to explore emotion analysis and related tasks in NLP. So far, we conducted a survey of the field in recent years, focusing in particular in the types of frameworks used in NLP research. 
We also showed that Large Language Models (LLMs) show significant gender bias, not only ascribing different emotions to men and women given the same events but doing so in line with existing stereotypes: men are overwhelmingly angry and women, overwhelmingly sad. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collaborators:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flor Miriam Plaza-del-Arco (Bocconi University)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alba Curry (University of Leeds)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gavin Abercrombie (Heriot-Watt University)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dirk Hovy (Bocconi University)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Research"></category></entry><entry><title>How did the Big 5 respond to the #MeToo Movement?</title><link href="/how-did-the-big-5-respond-to-the-metoo-movement.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-12-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Amanda Cercas Curry</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-12-03:/how-did-the-big-5-respond-to-the-metoo-movement.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Following is a review of my favorite mechanical keyboard.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Research"></category></entry><entry><title>Responding to Sexual Harassment (PhD Thesis)</title><link href="/responding-to-sexual-harassment-phd-thesis.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-12-03T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-12-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Amanda Cercas Curry</name></author><id>tag:None,2020-12-03:/responding-to-sexual-harassment-phd-thesis.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My thesis focused on abuse detection and mitigation in dialogue systems, particularly when it comes to female digital assitants: most commercial conversational AI assistants have female personas and this feminisation of AI can reinforce negative stereotypes of women as subservient, as these systems often produce submissive and sexualised responses to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My thesis focused on abuse detection and mitigation in dialogue systems, particularly when it comes to female digital assitants: most commercial conversational AI assistants have female personas and this feminisation of AI can reinforce negative stereotypes of women as subservient, as these systems often produce submissive and sexualised responses to abusive prompts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Research"></category></entry></feed>